YESENIA ROMÁN

Los Angeles, CA, US • (939) 207 -8641 romanlovesenia@gmail.com Website

Summary

I am a creative, resourceful, and bilingual librarian with over seven years of experience in reference, data acquisition, and cataloging services at large research institutions, and most recently at a public library. I enjoy helping people conduct research, learn, and make discoveries.

Professional experience

General Services Librarian, Part-time Inglewood Public Library, Main Library, Inglewood, CA. June 2022 - Nov 2022

- Provided reference services and technological assistance for patrons of all ages.
- Developed and led community programming to engage and educate the public.
- ♦ Curated book displays to showcase the collection.
- Designed promotional materials for programs, events, and social media.

Research Librarian April 2021- Aug. 2021

Prof. Curtis Deutsch Computational Laboratory, University of Washington (Remote, contract-based)

- Conducted a systematic literature review in Proguest and Web of Science for laboratory measurements of marine species thermal growth curves.
- ♦ Created a database of measurements extracted from published articles, tables, and figures.
- ♦ Organized citations and sources on Zotero shared library.

Research Librarian II (Data Services Specialist II) Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA Jan. 2019 - Oct. 2020

- ♦ Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.
- Data acquisition for six-plus research teams, leading to authorship in a peer-reviewed scientific article.
- Acquired and cataloged hundreds of data sources in differ- ent languages and formats.
- Advised and taught researchers best practices of data management and seeking.
- Established relationships with global vendors, researchers, and data providers in English and Spanish, leading to long-lasting data sharing and research collaborations between diverse organizations.

Research Librarian I (Data Services Specialist I) Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA

Jan. 2017 - Jan. 2019

- Managed the Institute's Help Desk, including supervising task delegation and resource allocation for 6 librarians
- ♦ Provided reference services for six-plus research teams, including assistance with research questions, library materials, resources, catalogs, and other library tools.

♦ Data acquisition for three annual studies by six-plus research teams, leading to my authorship in five peer-reviewed scientific articles.

Data Curator Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, Seattle, WA Dec. 2015 - Jan. 2017

- ♦ Dataset archiving in multiple formats and languages for an online public access catalog (GHDx) to ensure user agreement compliance.
- ♦ Managed Institute's catalog journal taxonomy by performing monthly reviews, additions, and merges.
- ♦ Biannual data source updates.

Digital Content Curator Market.Space Inc, (Remote)

Nov. 2015 - Dec. 2015

- ♦ Reviewed and created metadata for news articles on trav- el, venture capital, and gaming to train a machine-learning algorithm.
- ♦ Documented observations for taxonomy development and review.

Additional Experience

UX Research Assistant (June 2015 - Aug 2015)

Library of Congress: Office of Strategic Initiatives, Washington, DC

Web services Graduate Assistant (Aug 2013 - May 2015)

Social sciences, Health, and Education Library, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL

Special Education Paraprofessional (March 2013 - July 2013)

Chicago Tech Academy, Chicago, IL

Education

M.S. in Library and Information Sciences, Data Curation specialization

University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign

B.A. in Mesoamerican and Caribbean Anthropology

University of Puerto Rico, San Juan

Skills

Languages: English (Fluent) • Spanish (Native)

Microsoft Office Excel/Google Sheets

Adobe Illustrator/Procreate/Canvas

Intermediate knowledge of HTML and CSS.

Metadata skills

Project management

Cataloging

Reference

Bibliographic Research

Documentation